Hello everybody and welcome back to the
seventh episode of active inference
insights. I'm your host Darris Povi
Zwayne and today I have for the first
time two guests to bring you. Vicente
Raja is a research fellow at the
University of Murcia and affiliate
faculty of the Rotman Institute of
Philosophy at Western University in
Canada. His research lies at the
intersection of philosophy, cognitive
science, neuroscience and the history of
the sciences of the mind. In 2021 he was
the first author of the paper The Markov
Blanket Trick on the scope of the free
energy principle and active inference
which argues that  the FEP is not
the general principle it is claimed to
be and the active inference is not the
all-encompassing process theory it is
purported to be either.
We also have Jeff Beck. Jeff is a
computational neuroscientist studying
probabilistic reasoning in humans and
animals. He's also the senior machine
learning research lead at Versus and is
a critical contributor to the active
inference field writing among others the
paper Markov blankets and Bayesian
territories.
Guys, thank you so much
for joining me. It's an absolute
pleasure.
You know, we're talking off camera.
There may well be some points of
divergence but we are four days away
from Christmas at the time of recording.
And I think the baby Jesus would want us
to find some conciliation.
So
we will do we will do the most we can to
strike at differences and elucidate
differences and see but all in the
spirit of hopefully collaborative
science and collaborative thinking.
So in that with that in mind I think
where we could start is actually where
we have no issues with one another. So
looking at that paper, where are the
kind of points of just neutral, placid,
this is like a good starting point?
Vicente, I don't know whether you want
to start given that you wrote the paper
but where do you see so where Jeff's
work or the other key contributors
active inference, where do you see that
you know, some of the stuff they say is
actually pretty uncontroversial?
Good question.
So first of all, thank you for for for
having me here.
Um um I think
I could start with
very brief detour on why I wrote this
paper or why we wrote
this paper or
even
why the paper is the way it is.
Uh first of all, I wrote I started
writing it to actually to make sense of
the FEP and active inference for myself.
Right? To to try to see how it was
derived, the steps and actually section
two of the paper remains there just as
that, right? As starting with a random
dynamical system and just trying to go a
step by step there. So
this is I think one of the points in
which we converge is
at least from my point of view as a
person who works in the philosophy of
the cognitive science and the cognitive
science of themselves that
dynamical systems is a good way to look
at cognitive systems. So that's I think
we are in kind of the same camp.
Then
maybe the modeling
strategy that people like me that comes
from radical embodied cognitive science
and ecological psychology to model
dynamical systems and the Bayesian twist
of it that
you find in active inference are
slightly different, right? But you know,
this first step, this
first point I think is a is a is a point
of
convergence, too.
Um
but then
after after we we made sense I we think
of of of of the of the free energy of
the free energy principle and active
inference
uh
we
our point was okay, let's accept
all this formalism is good, right? We
don't challenge it. We just accept like
this is right.
But even accepting
that uh we have some questions about it
that have that those questions have to
do more on how different bits of the
formalism relate to different aspects of
cognitive systems and their relationship
with the environment, right? Um so and I
think this is where the divergence is
stronger. So I think the
convergence has to do with the with the
primacy I don't know if
the primacy if if if is the word but you
know
uh the
attributing importance to our dynamical
systems take on all these issues
and
the the good spirit of trying to find
formal methods to study it.
And our divergence I think has more to
do with uh
with
with some
conceptions on
how to best how to best address
dynamical systems or cognitive systems
in a dynamical terms and all that stuff.
Yeah. Excellent. Okay, that's that's
great. That's a great start. Um
Jeff, let's go to you.
Let's imagine that you're reading the
Markov Blanket Trick for the first time.
Where we will come to the divergences. I
promise you Oh well, I I I can tell a
story or I can well so for for I'll
start off in the spirit of this. I'll
start off with some with with the point
of agreement that I had with with with
the paper which was
one of one of the
there there there are two sort of often
discussed problems with like the FEP
literature.
One is is that it's very it's it's very
it uses idiosyncratic notation and it
can be very difficult to understand.
Um the other one is I is the thing that
apparently causes a lot of ire
particularly from philosophers and I
agree that this is a bit of a problem
which is there's a
uh a penchant for rhetorical excess
if I could say such a thing. Which is to
say I don't think that there's many many
problems with the FEP as a whole but I
think that it could be presented in a
more
compact and concise way that avoids, you
know, some of the more philosophical
claims that are often sprinkled
throughout these manuscripts. Um and I
do think that that would create both,
you know, and that this is something
that would create a both bit more
clarity and is something that like, you
know, people should poke back to. Like
when you say like when if you find
yourself and this is my personal view,
this is not like everyone's everyone who
does this but if you find yourself
putting the word thing in scare quotes,
you might want to think maybe you're
doing something wrong, right? I that's
just sort of like my knee-jerk response.
Um and so you know, that's that I think
is certainly a point where there's
definitely going to be some agreement
which is is that, you know, for me
mathematician simplify things, be
explicit, that's the beauty of it. Don't
add things to the equations that aren't
necessarily there. Um but of course
everyone every scientist does this,
right? We all want to sell our ideas. We
want to make we want to make them as big
as possible and so there is some of that
and I think that in particular because
the math is so difficult to understand
and follow, right? You know, has um
that those sorts of excesses have become
the focus, right? That's easier to sort
of like say oh that's, you know, this is
a problem, this is a problem.
Um and so yeah, that's that would be the
point of agreement. Uh if I were to
quickly and compactly summarize the
point of disagreement,
um it's it I I will do so by telling the
following story. So when I first came
across
um Karl Friston I was at the Gatsby at
the time.
And um so Karl Friston was like
literally in the building next door and
that's when I when I first came across
him and I saw him present his stuff and
I read a couple of his papers and um for
me
there were many things that I was like
concerned about. Let's just leave it at
that. Let's say concerned. We can get
into it more later. But the one thing
that wasn't controversial at all in my
opinion was the Markov blanket part of
the story.
And that I think
and I and my hope is is that, you know,
is that as this conversation proceeds
we'll be able to like I'll be able to
explain what I mean by that
and maybe
come to some sort of consensus. So I'm
happy to do that now but I I feel like
yeah. Yeah, yeah, we we will we will
unpick stuff gradually. That's quite a
that's quite a good irony.
Uh the the Markov blanket was kind of
the point of ah, this one this bit
works.
Yeah, I mean I I take your point that
the maths ought to be elegant,
parsimonious
um as much as possible but unfortunately
or or fortunately
any grand unifying theory comes with it
the philosophy, the cognitive science,
the neuroscience, the theoretical
biology and so on. Um and so I think
it's an inevitable consequence that we
get wrapped into epistemological and
ontological questions. But we will do
our hardest to unpick them with
simplicity because I think that's
actually all that we're aiming for.
So I read the I read the paper
obviously. I read it multiple times and
I read the the commentaries and and your
response to the commentaries.
And for me there were
about two or three distinct critiques of
the free energy principle and active
inference that I think we could have a
good conversation about.
The first is that Markov blankets fail
to capture all possible types of
conditional independencies. So for
example, candles. The candle
relationship to the external environment
or groups of people, cultures,
societies, their relationship to uh the
whatever those external dynamics are
that they're shielded from by the Markov
blanket. And then linked to that and
then I'll leave it there is that these
things, to use Jeff's quote marks, have
properties certain things have
properties that cannot be captured by
the Markov blanket formalism. And
Vicente, you mentioned relational
properties and constitutive
self-organization.
So, I don't know whether you want to
take those as two separate things, one
being
um the incapacity of the Markov blanket
to capture all types of conditional
independencies,
um and then those two strands, the
constitutive self-organization and the
relational properties. I don't know
whether you want to take them separately
or whether you think they fall under the
same blanket, if you'll pardon the pun.
Okay, we'll do it separately. Jeff is
the point I want to make. Let's start
there with
um
the incapacity, as I said, for the
Markov blanket
to capture all conditional
independencies. And let's use for sake
of simplicity this uh
object that I selected before, the
candle. What What does the candle tell
us about the free energy principle?
Vicente, please.
Um actually, we we use candle flames
because it is an example that was in the
in in the in the literature to write.
It seems, if I remember well, I haven't
I haven't reread the
the paper, so I might be not fully
accurate about what was claimed there.
But, if I remember well, the issue with
the Markov blanket is is is that what we
can take as blanket states are are
changing too fast in time.
So, so so there's no way to
to find them and to and to know and to
and to measure them over time in in in
the way that is required by
the
formalism. And if I remember well,
Thomas Parr talks about it in his in his
commentary to the to the to the Markov
blanket tricks. It's actually the only
commentary that concedes that we might
be right in something in some which is
an interesting thing, but it's okay.
And he claims that it could be solved in
if if
in this kind of
systems or in this kind of things quotes
uh
we look to instead of looking to states
themselves, we can look to to to
densities of of states, you know, we can
try to model those states. And I think
this is an
interesting move
that points out why we think
that there are there is more about the
Markov blanket
uh
than just to say, "Oh, no, it's just the
simple answer to how to differentiate
this, you know, the internal and the
external states, right? The The
the
the free energy principle
uh and and active inference
doesn't really tell you whether you have
to choose states or densities of states
as uh the blanket, right? So, you are
putting assumption extra
assumptions there on how you choose to
do that. And this is kind of the overall
thread of
the critique. When we claim the free
energy principle is not the principle it
it it claims to be, we we are not
claiming that it cannot be used as the
as the as the principle of least action
to, you know, to to write down some
equations, but that
that it seems like just from this
principle and from answering two simple
question, what is to be a thing and how
to to um
differentiate it from the environment,
you have everything.
And we try to to to posit examples in
which you always need an extra step. You
always need extra
assumptions that that are not always
clear in the when you only appeal to the
formalism.
So, this is the role of our of how of
why we think that the fact that candle
flames as an as an example that was in
the in the literature why candle flames
are
important. I think they point out that
you always need you always need extra
assumptions that are not always clear in
the in
when you only appeal to the formalism.
Right. Um
perfect. That's a really nice exposition
of of the claim that you're making. Uh
Jeff, I'll jump to you then. Um
it would be, you know,
we'll talk to that would be wonderful.
And I think actually with specific
mention, if possible, of this dichotomy
that Vicente mentioned, which is are we
talking about states, some kind of
ontological thing, again, or are we
talking about probability densities? And
where does that line become
blurry? What actually is that
difference? Or is it just that we're
just making a kind of false identity
claim? What What's the sort of
What's really going on here?
Um so, I think that the best way the
best way to respond is would be uh so
the the the the short the short, pithy,
and dismissive of answer is to say, "I I
solved the pro- I solved the flame
problem." I wish I could share my
screen. I have some really cool like I
really I have some really cool graphics.
Um so, what one of the one of the other
problems that that that you know, when
conveying the free energy free energy
principle that um
it's its proponents have faced is the
fact, you know, I sort of said this, the
math is really hard. And in order to in
order to make it tractable, a lot of
additional assumptions get put in along
the way just to make the math easier.
Right? And some of those assumptions are
necessary to make, you know, so
many of those assumptions are not
actually part of the free energy
principle by itself. Right? Or part of
the Markov blanket story on its own.
Right? But are done to make the math
easier. Like when I first came across
the FEP, I thought there was no
difference between active inference and
KO control theory.
Right? And the reason why was because
when they go to actually solve the
equations, they make some additional
assumptions to make the math easier so
that it ends up being equivalent to KO
control theory. But if you go in and
sort of say, "Well, what actually is
the principle itself?" As derived either
as Karl does it from um
uh
statistical physics or the way I prefer
to do it, which is directly from
information theory, right? That's not
the case. Right? The actual like
objective function of active inference
involve solving these like complicated
path integrals and things like that. But
to make the problem easier, to make the
math easier, to make it more solvable,
additional like factorial assumptions
are built in. And a lot of people jump
on the fact that like, "Oh, it's like
you have all these additional
assumptions that kind of like But those
are done often for like computational
reasons. They're not necessarily part of
the theory." We like to joke that, you
know, you know, everybody talks about
the generality of the path integral
formulation of uh and and James Maxent
and how it's mappable onto statistical
physics. What people often forget is the
problem with the path integral
formulation is you actually have to
solve path integrals, which is a serious
pain in the butt.
And so, this is sort of like my summary
like one one of the things that has
contributed to a lot of confusion has
been these additional mathematical
simplifications that are then taken to
be part of the theory when they are not.
Um in regards to the flame story, cuz I
know I gave like a
pithy and dismissive answer and I'd like
I don't, you know, that was just
I will fix that now in the interest of
politeness.
Um
What The reason that I didn't think that
the Markov blanket story was like at all
controversial was because of its link to
systems identification theory.
Right? The Markov blanket itself
basically just specifies the domain in
which systems identification theory can
apply.
Right? So, the idea is that so what So,
how does it So, when you
I don't have, you know, so system,
environment, inputs, outputs, right? If
you're doing systems identification
theory, you're basically saying, "Well,
what is the system doing? How What is
its input-output?" This is very
colloquial here, right? We can make this
more specific. What is its input-output
relationship? In order to do systems
identification theory, right? You need
to know what that input-output
relationship That's the goal to figure
out what that input-output relationship.
And if you see a particular input-output
relationship, that gives you the label
for that kind of system.
Right? It's a system of type X because
it has this input-output relationship.
The Markov blanket is basically just
specifies the domain in which you are
going to do a statistical version of
systems identification theory. Right?
It's the domain of the inputs and
outputs of the So, when somebody says,
"I have a big system and there's lots of
stuff in it, and I'm going to segregate
out a little system from it."
The mere fact that you can do that to
When you say like, "This is a
subsystem." You have already said that
there's a Markov blanket.
Does that make sense? Right? All
subsystems have blankets. Like by
definition.
It's It's It's sort of implicit That's
And that's why I didn't never thought
that it was controversial because what
do we do? We want to say, "Well, that's
a subsystem. That's an important thing.
It gets its own label.
And so, it has a blanket." It's like
it's
It's It's just It's the way we do
systems identification theory. So, I
don't know.
I want to hear if I want to see if
Vicente has a response before I move on
to the flame in particular. I mean, that
that's that's kind of I
That's That's That's the That's what I
read when I when I was reading the
literature more. Uh
it's kind of it's it's it's
it's uh
non-controversial
for the people who work on it in that
sense. Like you you uh you identify a
system.
Uh there's therefore there's there's
there's a blanket and there's an
external state.
I think
and part of the
Markov blanket trick is to see different
issues we find with that. That that for
many systems we are interested in, we
don't see it's to be so straight
forward. Like we when when we model with
dynamical systems
for instance with the HKB model
uh to the the behavior of two coupled
oscillator where the where the
collective variable is relative phase.
Our system is the couple oscillators.
So you can put a blanket around it, I
guess.
But then what's the environment?
Uh
it's it's it's the it's the blanket
pulled on the phase space of the
relative phase
which is not a property of any of the
two things there, right? So I mean I
kind of understand the abstract sense,
but then I don't exactly see how this
apply to kind of systems that we are
interested in.
Right. So I'll I'll I'll I'll just
quickly respond. So so the problem with
the whole Markov blanket part of the
story is that there's just too god damn
many Markov blankets, right? You have
this big complicated system.
Right? And even you know, and even if
you're going to limit yourself as they
often do in the FEP literature to like
static Markov blankets, right? Where one
once a particle or a constituent
component or whatever has been assigned
to either environment, blanket, or
object, it's always there, right? So
this is a situation where there's no
such thing as matter transfer.
Right? Which is the why the flame case
by the way like doesn't work, right? The
flame flames have Markov blankets, but
they're not static. Right? Because as
the matter
you know, as it burns and moves in and
the fuel comes in and and exhaust goes
out, right? The matter is constantly So
if you if your definition of a blanket
is that it's tied to matter, then yeah,
you're right. Like you can't do a flame
at all.
But that's that that that So but putting
that issue aside, the problem with
Markov blankets is is that they're
everywhere. You have a glass of water.
Every single fluid element in the glass
of water. So what's a fluid element?
Right? You take a glass of water and you
draw a little circle. I mean obviously
it's not it's 3D, right? But But an
arbitrary fluid volume has a blanket.
Right? And we and and we know this like
when we do finite element methods for
simulating them, we draw the we take our
glass of water and we make it into lots
of little cubes and all the cubes are
connected and the boundaries between the
cubes form the blanket.
There's too many blankets.
Blankets are absolutely everywhere.
Right? And they and their their
boundaries are often completely like
where you're going to put your blanket
is the hardest problem to solve.
Right? And I think that that that that
the free energy literature has not
worried too much about the problem of
where you're drawing the blanket because
the idea was if you've got a blanket,
then it's a subsystems have blankets.
Right? We're interested in subsystems.
And so now we can just like put that
problem aside. But it's a really
difficult problem to say, well, what is
the principle that tells me that this
gets a blanket?
Right? Why is why is a blanket that's
around, you know, a bubble
rising through my glass of water the
right blanket as opposed to an arbitrary
blanket around a fluid element that has
no bubbles in
it,
right? And I don't think that that that
that question has not been adequately
addressed in the literature, you know,
you know,
in my opinion.
But I believe that that there is a
notion that is sort of implicit in the
FEP approach
that handles that. And so when when I
when I sat down and tried to solve the
flame problem,
I asked myself, well, what additional
principle and that this might make
Vicente happy, right? There is an
additional principle. He was absolutely
right. I think the principle was
implicit, um but the additional
principle is like how do you choose your
blankets? Well, you choose them for
parsimony and simplicity, right? In
other words, we use the scientific
method. Right?
You take all the ways that you you have
this complicated interacting system, you
take all the ways that you can draw the
you know, boundaries in them. And
there's like an uncount you know, not
uncountable, but there's a really large
number of different ways that you could
draw your blankets. And the way you pick
the one that's important is the one that
results in the greatest simplification
of the of the resulting dynamics. This
is basically like mean you can think of
this as mean field or coarse graining if
you're a physicist, right? That's what a
coarse graining is is that you segregate
your system into macroscopic variables
or macroscopic components if it's a
mechanical system. And the choice that
you make as to how you're going to do
that is to is to basically make the
system as simple as possible. If you
take that approach, then you have if you
take that approach and apply it to the
flame situation in particular, that's
exactly what you discover, right? You
discover that the blanket of a flame,
right? is just outside the reaction zone
where all of the exothermic reactions
are going on.
Okay. Excellent. Uh I think we're
agreeing too much.
I think
that's going very well.
I love the the flame problem. I like
that. Yeah, yeah. That's gorgeous.
I I really wish I could share my screen
cuz I I queued up some videos and like,
you know, and and had some figures that
I was like just in case. Well, if you
have But the the flame case really is
cool. I'm going to publish that soon.
I'm just working on I'm I'm trying to
get like a whole I'm working on a
um
I took some fake I took some data from
you guys know what particle linea Well,
you know, everyone knows what Conway's
Game of Life is. So this is Conway's
Game of Life but for interacting
particles.
And so they get these particles to do
cool things and so you can put in a
random bunch of particles and they form
a cell membrane and the cell membrane
grows stuff like flagella. And so we
applied it to that situation as well and
what you find is that the blankets are
changing over time and as they change
the identity of the object also changes,
which is exactly what you want, right?
And the reason for this is because the
blanket itself the blanket alone is
meaningless, right? It just specifies
the domain in which you're going to do
your system identification or
dimensionality reduction. Right? What
really defines an object's type is the
statistics of the domain.
Right? And so as a result, you can watch
these cells evolve and as the statist as
the statistics of the various boundaries
in the system cuz there's more than one.
Um uh change, so does the identity of
the associated object, right? Which is
really what I want. This is really all
about labeling stuff.
Right?
Right. And in order to label stuff by
type, you need a blanket and the way
that you identify a type is by the
statistics of the blanket. Okay, this is
really useful. Um because yeah, I think
we found agreement with the idea that
the FEP needs to integrate some
historicity, some dynamics, and perhaps
even changing identities of you as
you've just outlined there, Jeff.
I think Well, I I think the the critical
thing is is recognizing and this is
implicit in everything that Carl writes,
right? It's it it just needs to be made
more explicit, right? He says the
blanket defines the phenotype. That is a
misleading statement. It's true, but
it's misleading, right? The correct
statement is the statistics of the
blanket define the phenotype.
Right. Right? It's not just the blanket
itself. That the blanket itself is just
a domain.
Yeah. Right? It's just where Yeah, it So
yeah. Well, I think this is a um
this problem I think has started to be
remedied within the active inference
literature um because I don't know if
you guys have noticed this as well, but
there's been a move to turn the internal
generative model to a generative model
that actually both encompasses across
the Markov blanket the external or the
internal states. So this is something
that Maxwell Ramstead makes very clear
in his um
in this year's paper um physics of
belief.
That to put it roughly.
Um but I think there is a there is still
a slight point of difference here and I
wonder whether it's just a semantic one.
Jeff, you still talk about internal
states or the particle or the thing, the
system, and the environment.
Whereas Vicente is talking about coupled
oscillators.
And the way that I think about this is
we can either have an intrinsic or an
extrinsic relation between let's say
external dynamics and internal dynamics.
Now what does that mean? Well, an
external relation would be something
like a causal relationship.
So the A and B retain their identity
despite the fact that they're causally
related. An intrinsic relation is
something more like a familial relation.
Okay? If I am my you know, my mother is
defined as my mother because of the
relationship that she has with me.
So in many in many ways I find that this
distinction that you guys are carving
here might be neatly mapped onto that
distinction. Vicente, I'm going to start
with you.
Do you think that a mistake that the FEP
makes might be to try and carve out an
external relation?
So we've got A enacting changing B which
changes A, when really the focus should
be on the dynamics of the entire system
as a whole in the way that sort of Evan
Thompson and um those who followed spoke
about these kind of coupled dynamic
systems where the identity is in the
mutual coupling.
Good question. I mean I I I I would like
to to just point out I think Jeff has
pointed
uh
has pointed out uh
what our issue is.
Um
and and I agree with
with pretty much everything he he has
said in that in that regard, right? Our
issue basically was that I mean we have
nothing against Markov blankets
blankets as as a methodological tool as
a mathematical tool,
but we would like to know more about how
you select the blanket because we think
that
depending on how you select the blanket
you are interested in, you might be
doing two
different things, right? Um
and and that and that
it's there are it's other parts other
fundamental parts of your theory
what makes you to to to select a
blanket, let's say, for the organism.
Uh
and then the organism has internal
states and the environment is the
external states. Or if you are an
ecological psychologist like me, you
want a blanket for the organism
environment system.
And then everything is internal states
and it's not clear what the what the
what the external state could be there,
right? You can also choose a blanket on
the organism environment system and a
nested one. And then another blanket.
But it's it's blankets all the way down,
man. All the way to protons. They got
blankets too.
So as as a mathematical tool, so to
speak, there are too many blankets,
right?
Yeah.
But how you choose them reflects what
kind of
what kind of
fundamental theory you have in mind. And
And when I say fundamental theory, I
think about psychology, cognitive
science,
right? So
if you for instance think that the
organism has this input-output mapping
and all the relevant computations
happens inside, so all the control of
behavior, all all the are all the all
the all the perceptual inference is
depending on the internal states, you
you are first you are
likely a
cognitive scientist of the mainstream,
right? And you want the the blanket in
the organism and the external states are
basically inputs,
right? Uh,
while if you are an ecological
psychologist and you think that to
understand perception, for instance, the
first step is to see the structures in
the environment,
those
structures are relevant in themselves
and contribute to perception as much as
the internal states of the
organism there. So then you probably
don't take those structures to be just
input, right? So
my my point being here that I totally
agree that there are too many blankets
and that the selection process depends
on deeper theories
that go maybe beyond the free energy
principle as such. And you can then you
can use the free energy principle as a
method to to develop those
those theories, right? Yeah, so yeah, so
this is the
I could I mean, my take on this is as I
I completely agree, right? There there
there is a sort of hidden additional
principle. But I think that one of the
reasons this got neglected in the free
energy literature is because the whole
point was
we're always drawing blankets. You can
draw it anywhere and this theory still
applies,
right? Doesn't matter where you put your
blanket,
right? I can still I can still treat the
system as if it is doing inference over
its environment. It doesn't you know,
exactly you know, that that that was
sort of like I think the reason why the
the the sort of additional like how do
you select your blanket problem was
neglected was because they were trying
to show the principle always works,
right? Um, that's sort of my my my
defense of of of of of Karl Friston's
world is that like there's a reason they
skipped the problem because they don't
know it wasn't the important problem,
right? The important problem was it
doesn't matter how you draw your
blankets, you still get you still can
apply the rest of the principle. So if
you decide that that your system is a
cell, that's fine. If it's a collection
of cells, that still works. If it's gets
and so on,
right?
So our question was then I think I think
this question was in the Markov blanket
trick, too. What if your blanket is the
is the is the organism environment
system? What are the external states
to that system that the system infers,
so to speak?
If If yeah, if if you're if you're yeah,
so if your blanket is like the whole
universe, I don't I'm going to go with
it's Christmas. I'm going to go with
baby Jesus.
Okay.
Very good. Right now
Right, I mean, you know, the So
I think that that's counter to the to to
the reason why we want to define
blankets in the first place. And the
reason is because we want to label
things,
right? And the reason we want to label
things is you know, is because well, it
it simplifies our lives, right? If I can
look at say that's a cat, that's another
kind of cat, right? Then not you know, I
can sort of use you know, that you know,
use those labels because they make my my
life easier, right? They make prediction
easier about what's going to happen and
things like that,
right? That's the reason why we want to
have labels and the Markov blanket just
sort of said, well, you know, this is a
potential place. So that that And the
reason I make this argument is I do
think that implicit in the whole
approach, well not necessarily as
explicitly made in the literature as it
should have been,
is that the goal is to label things. The
goal is to come up with phenotypes. And
since the goal is to come up with
phenotypes, you can ask the question,
well, why would we want to do that? And
the answer is parsimony, right? We want
a simple compact representation of our
world.
And the way we do it is by taking big
complicated things made of lots of
little parts and giving them a single
label that describes a lot of their
general properties and features. And
that is exactly what the Markov blanket
does or is capable of doing. And so that
also tells you, which is why I like in
my world, right? That's the additional
principle. It was implicit. I'm I want
to make it explicit that the way that we
choose which blankets to focus on is
like the way we do science. It's based
on simplifying dynamics for the purposes
of prediction and data compression.
Jeff, I may jump in here um and perhaps
speak on Vicente's behalf. I'm very
happy for him to jump over me and and
and clarify this. But I think a
question comes up here, which is
so we're we're interested in labeling,
we're interested in
describing
coupled systems.
So how come when
in the FEP literature we draw blankets,
they so
coincidentally happen to fall elegantly
on what we intuitively believe to be
things and their blankets. So for
example, yes, you say, okay, it's
because well, we see cats and glasses
and humans and planets and like why
wouldn't we carve blankets around them?
But why in the sense does it work to
carve blankets around them if we're
dealing more in information exchange
than
how the object appears to our sensorium.
And given that
as a mathematician or a physicist, what
does that say about the mapping between
kind of our perception and the
information transfer that we're being
able to describe via the Markov blanket?
I think very hard about that question.
Um
because my my knee-jerk response is to
like is to launch into my like what is
science for discussion, which is
probably not going to directly address
what it is that you what it is that you
want me to to address.
Um
when
when the issue is still if the issue is
still like um
Let's see. So it there are two there are
two things going on here, right? One is
what do we do with the information that
the universe gives us? How do we
categorize it, label it, and make it
simple and easy to understand? And then
the other issue is is well, what is you
know, what is any subsystem necessarily
doing?
Right? And those are very different
issues,
right? When we talk about the when we
ask the question though, why do we call
this a subsystem and and you know, and
then like I'm trying to cut it in half
and like this not and and this not a
subsystem.
And that choice is arbitrary, right?
That's one of the the the lessons that
I'm trying to drive home here is is that
like you can draw a blanket around
anything.
The question is why would you?
Right? Having drawn a blanket, all of
the free energy mechanic the Bayesian
mechanics all apply, right? But what why
would I draw a particular blanket? And
then it really is because it's useful to
us, right? If we could just like have a
computer that simulated absolutely
everything,
right? And that didn't and it was like I
don't know, cost like 5 cents to run, we
would totally do that.
And we would be happy and we wouldn't
care about labels, right? But we don't
have that ability, right? We are trying
to construct these you know, things that
we can wrap our brains around. We're
trying to simplify things,
you know, to make them parsable and
understandable to us.
And so that's why we would choose a
particular set of blankets. Now, but
again, the point though is and the
reason why I think that there wasn't
enough emphasis in the free energy
literature is that all of once you have
established that there's a blanket,
which you can always do, like the rest
of it just follows,
right? All the stuff about, you know, is
it effectively doing is it behaving as
if it's performing inference on its
environment? Yes, right? I think the
more interesting question that Vicente
brings up in the paper, which which
which I read yesterday,
that I thought was a really great
question,
um was had to do with with well, which
is the environment and which is the
object?
Right?
Because even this parsimony principle
that I just established, right? Doesn't
help with that because I just said
simplify the global dynamics.
Like what what you know, what what um
macroscopic theory
does the best that happens to have this
partitioning?
Um and that doesn't tell you which is
the But this is But this is where I
think you now need to move back into
physics land,
right? So people like I really like the
work of Jeremy England,
um and uh and everyone loves like
Schrödinger's little
I I Is it What is life? Is that the
title of it, right? Um where there is
you know,
in in in that work there is like a a the
of how you There is a notion of how you
tell which is the agent and which or
which is the object and which is the
environment which is the agent and which
is the environment. And it basically has
to do with energy flow.
Right? So, you could sort of say, "Oh,
well, you know,
the organism is the thing that takes in
energy and produces entropy."
Right? And then once you've done that,
if you're talking about a physical
system, right?
You know, then now you have something
that that does in fact uniquely identify
We know which is which. Which you don't
get out of it That's my point, right?
You don't get that out of a out of a
simplicity parsimony type principle.
Right?
Cuz then well, I'm not sure whether you
want to Yes. Go to that second point or
whether you want to loop back to my
first point about the mapping between
the supposedly arbitrary epistemological
tool-based approach of the Markov
blanket. And actually, maybe
how that maps onto onto logically, at
least what we perceive. I don't know
which one you want to start with. Yeah.
I think that that that that the last
thing or the the this last
intervention by by by Jeff.
I think it he states and I think we we
are going to agree here.
He He literally states the Markov
blanket trick.
Right? That that as as as soon as you
put the blanket on top of a a system,
right? Or whatever you choose with all
these
pragmatic stuff, then you can do
Bayesian inference. Right? You as you
put
the blanket, you have now the so to
speak the data structure with latent
variables, observables, and
internal ones to do that.
And I think we
agree that or we could agree that this
is the Markov blanket trick.
While Jeff thinks this is good, right?
It's It's It's
It's good.
We think it's so-so, right? But But that
kind kind kind of be
the point, right? So,
I think the Markov blanket trick is good
if you are already convinced, for
instance, that perception is a kind of
inference.
And then it
gives you very precise mathematical
tools to model that.
Now,
if you think like some
crazy people like me, right?
that
perception is not something that, you
know, something that the internal states
of an organism
the internal state states of an organism
do in order to know the external states,
so to speak.
But it's a property of the
organism-environment system.
Then this data structure doesn't really
map very well with what we want to do.
Or maybe it does, but we don't see how.
And and And and part And part of of our
paper is to is to try to to express, you
know, to to state these doubts. On Okay,
how could I apply this if I think this
other thing, right?
And
and then
second part,
which is what the what the um why the
blanket falls exactly where it needs to
to be. I think this is a part of First,
this is a part of
a conversation I've had like dozens of
time with
Maxwell,
right? He He is He is the person I've
talked more about this. So, we've talked
about this. And actually, in in their
commentary to the Markov blanket trick,
they talk about this
paper he has with
Dalton,
the weak Markov
blankets, right? That they prove that
there are a lot of them, right? Like
Like as soon as you have dimensions, you
know. And
And
our question in our response was, "Yes,
I mean,
but the point is not that you have a lot
of them. It's how you choose the right
one. So, how you choose for, let's say,
for the visual system, how you choose
the blanket in the sensory receptors,
so to speak, right? And And I think Jeff
has been
touching upon that, right? In in in in
in some of some of the things he he has
been
saying today.
Before I move back to Jeff, could you
just maybe for the audience expound upon
what you meant by this sort of
distinction
makes sense when we take for granted
perception as inference? I think that'll
be quite an interesting avenue just to
unpick a little bit further just so the
audience knows exactly what you mean by
that.
Yeah. So, uh
Long story short,
uh the common theory of perception, at
least
since Helmholtz, but most likely since
Descartes or even
beyond that, is that uh perception is is
a is a form of inference, right? So, the
our mind-brain is in
the business of inferring
the real environment, so to speak, from
uh impoverished stimulation. So, what we
get in in in a
our sensory systems is
usually
uh ambiguous, not not not very
informative or not completely
informative. And generally,
uh insufficient as to know what is the
exact cause of the of that input, right?
Like
the the typical example is is is that is
that, you know,
uh
a small closed object can give you the
same input that than a larger object
that is farther
away, right? They can occupy the same
angle in your in your retina, blah blah.
So,
the mainstream
theory is that the brain is in
the business of
inferring the real properties of the
environment from this impoverished
input. And it That's so because it it
can use
prior knowledge, memory, experience, you
know, to build up a
good model of the real environment.
Ecological psychologists think,
along with many other people that come
that come at least from
William James.
William James explicitly claims that
this kind of
of approach, this
inferential approach to perception, is
pure mythology.
I'm I mean, it's kind of the way they
wrote in the 19th century, right? But
The point being is that for ecological
psychologists, the kind of prior
knowledge you need in order for the
inference to work
is very difficult to justify.
Um
So, they think that
perception is more of a relation of
rich information that comes from the
environment and the and the internal
dynamics. And the relation itself is
what
uh perception is. But we don't need an
inference
because we don't need to go from
impoverished stimulation to the real
environment. But the
the There's a way to understand
perceptual
information that gives you all you need
without the need of prior
knowledge in order to get grips, so to
speak, with the real environment.
So, it's kind of a direct undirect stuff
or perception as an inference or
perception as an as information
detection. Now,
I have to put again because I've talked
with Maxwell a lot about this. So, I
just want to put up
uh
sort sort of
um
asterisk here, right?
You can still see how the internal
dynamics change in order to couple with
this rich
information in terms of some form of
Bayesian inference because Bayesian
inference is yes, you know, you can you
can describe the the path of a dynamical
system towards an attractor in terms of
a probability density of the state. So,
there's there's a form to Maybe there's
a form to use inference
that is the Bayesian inference way in
which you can capture both
of them.
I'm still in an ongoing discussion with
Maxwell about that.
Yeah, this is
This is the as if part of the free
energy principle, right? The math tells
us that everything, right? behaves as if
it is performing Bayesian inference.
Right? It doesn't tell us two additional
things, like how shitty that inference
is.
It could be really Like a rock is
performing Bayesian inference. It's just
not doing a very good job.
Um
and uh you know, but it But that's But
that's That That just follows That just
follows entirely from the mathematics of
it, right? Is Is that Is it It is an as
if description, right? The The
description of anything,
you know, it is always an available
description of a phenomenon that it is
that it functions as if it's performing
inference, right? Um whether it's
actually performing inference or doing
like solving the right inference problem
or or however you want to put that, um
is not is not explicitly addressed. And
I think a really interesting question,
you know, so for example, when you know,
when one applies the the the energy
principle in practice, there's always
this implicit assumption that whatever
the thing is doing is it's actually
doing inference correctly.
Right? There's an optimal inference
engine sort of like hidden inside. Now,
they can get away with this, right?
Because what goes on on the inside
doesn't matter.
Right? And what defines the object is
the what defines the thing is the
statistics of its boundary. And so, if
you have like a really boring boundary
statistics, like you're a rock,
right? Then you don't need a very
sophisticated like like the inference
engine that you would actually use to
sort of say, "Well, what is the you
know, what does this rock have to infer
about the external world in order to be
a rock?" And the answer is very little.
So, you kind of get a lot of these
things for free, but it is an as if
description, right? It's not like you
know, it's it's just an you know, like I
said, this is you know, another way to
get to the free energy principle is from
a purely information theoretic approach,
right? And I prefer that approach
because all of this stuff makes a little
bit more sense. Right? You're not sort
of saying like the rock is doing
inference, you're saying, you know, the
rock is behaving as it becomes more
clear that this is sort of an as if
argument, right? As opposed to it's
there's literally an internal state in
the rock that is computing, you know,
the probability that the that the water
in the stream is about to change. No,
it's not, right?
Yeah, yeah, I
I had the only because you have to infer
to be a rock. Yeah, yeah, yeah. I um
I was did a good podcast with Adam
Safron a couple of days ago and I said
my favorite two words in the free energy
principle are looks like.
Um but as as if it's that
As if as if is the one that I like to
pick up.
Yeah, as if looks like. Uh no, I think
that's I think that's a useful
clarification.
Um
unless you're a panpsychist and then
they might be coming for you.
Um What's wrong with panpsychism? I
don't understand why everyone's down on
panpsychism.
I actually don't mind it. I'm kind of
into the spookier versions, but I think
they'd love you. Well, they might they
might be keen to
perhaps I can't speak for Philip Goff
and everyone else, but they might be
keen to bring into question the validity
of that as if or looks like, but we need
not go there. Um I wanted to sort of
I do want to This was one of the
critiques I kind of identified, so I do
want to just get some clarity on that.
Um
And I I'll actually quote Vicente here.
So, this is Vicente's response to the
commentaries.
Um
The extent to which something counts as
a thing depends on the choice of market
Markov blanket partition, which can be
adjusted according to the needs of the
model. There is an ambiguity here. On
the one hand, it is claimed that things
are what they are by definition, even if
boundaries do not really align with the
intuitive ones for ordinary things.
On the other hand, when the FEP presents
possible examples of things like brains
or cells, the Markov blanket always
falls in the right place from the
intuitive point of view.
That probably puts more elegantly the
point I was trying to make earlier.
Yeah.
Does that shed any clarity on where I
was going? And Jeff, do you think you
do you have a kind of riposte to that?
I I almost hate to do what I'm about to
do. Can you Can you give me the quote
one more time? My brain
I'll give you I'll give you the I'll
give you the That was a That was a
lengthy quote and I I'm going to need to
hear it one more time to fully absorb
and appreciate it. Okay. So, I'll do it
so
amended version a shortened version. On
the one hand, it is claimed that things
are what they are by definition, even if
the boundaries do not really align with
the intuitive ones for ordinary things.
On the other hand, when the FEP presents
possible examples of things like brains
or cells, the Markov blanket always
falls in the right place from the
intuitive point of view.
Okay. So, I do have a response to that
and that that that that this goes back
to the notion that what defines a thing,
where you get this sort of notion of
phenotype, is the statistics of the
blanket.
And so, that gives you the ability to
sort of say, "Oh, this is like you know,
like right now I'm I'm I'm concerned
with brains."
So, I all I have to do is ask, "What is
the statistics, you know,
what is the statistics of the of the
brain blanket?"
Right? And then that's the thing I'm
currently going to investigate.
Right? And so, you know, but I do think
that this does illustrate the you know,
one of the issues which we've been
talking about, which is is that like
there is this sort of fundament you
know, if you were going to like de novo
start just putting blankets on
everything in the world,
right?
There isn't an explicit principle
present in the FEP that tells you how to
do that.
Right? There's this additional
principle, which is like you know, that
that that I that led to the you know,
the algorithm that I used to discover
the the blankets of flames, which is
like parsimony,
right? But it's it's not Now, the reason
why that that they don't worry about
that is because it's
the the implicit in every single thing
in the FEP literature is knows that we
are labeling stuff.
Right? I have the freedom to label what
I'm interested in.
And having done that, right? That sort
of tells me what the blanket statistics
are going to be.
Um I'll just add one other thing. The
reason I prefer like the information
theoretic derivation of the FEP is
because is is because um the way that
works is you start out with a
probability distribution over blankets.
Right? It's like this is like is and you
take it's a it's a it's a it's a James
MaxEnt or MaxEnt's kind of approach and
you sort of say like, "Hey, like I have
some laws that tell me how the universe
works and those are some constraints,
right? And then I also have I want to
find a I want to find some subset of my
system that has these statistics. Those
statistics are then definitional." This
leads to you know, sort of Langevin
equationy type things, right? That you
can then solve, which tells you how the
world has to be, how the individual
particles in the system have to behave
if you're doing it in particle space, um
in order for that thing to exist.
Right? And it has to exist because you
imposed it as a constraint when you did
your sort of MaxEnty thing.
Right? Um
If you have it If you have that in mind,
what you're really asking when you sort
of when you take this sort of FEP, you
know, when you when you sort of we we If
you take this sort of um
Can I Can I use the phrase ontological
potential? Or is that going to make
people upset?
Right? One of the things that comes out
if you if you take this sort of free
approach, you're basically like, "Look,
these statistics define an object type."
Right? And now what I want to know is I
want to know like, "Well, what's inside?
What's outside? Like what kind of
environment it can live in? Like what
kind of you know, you know, what what
does it have to be made of?"
Right? You can just
apply that those statistics as part of a
constraint, do MaxEnt and get all of the
equations that tell you how what kind of
environment this sort of thing can live
in.
Right? But the starting point was like
I'm interested in like this kind of
thing.
Right? And the reason why we call it an
ontological potential is because you
sort of said like
you've all you've started by saying this
is my definition of something.
And free energy is literally a potential
function.
Like when you do it in this MaxEnty way.
It's literally a potential function. So,
free energy is an ontological potential.
But it does start by saying this is the
thing I this is the thing I'm interested
in. It starts by specifying those
statistics, the statistics of a given
object type.
Vicente, do you want to add anything to
that? I mean, I'm wondering whether from
a philosophical, if you're putting your
philosophical hat on, what
presuppositions
just that kind of as as Jeff said, like
we're starting from like this is a
thing, what philosophical
presuppositions does that uh entail?
Yeah, I mean,
uh
I'm
I'm kind of happy with that, right? You
choose your thing
and you do you apply the methods you
want to. So, I'm
we we we we really don't have anything
with when I say with the the authors of
of of of the paper, of course, but
myself
also, uh we really don't have any
any
uh criticism to that.
Our
uh criticism and actually it was that
paper was published along with a few
more that were talking about that.
There's this this this one by Jelle
Bruineberg et al. on the Perils of
Blanket and Miguel Aguilera and Chris
Buckley had another one there, right? Um
So,
so to speak, if you are up front with,
"Look, this is what I took to be what I
take to be a thing or this is my thing
of
of interest for these reasons and then
I'm I'm going to apply the Markov
blanket here."
If the methods work, well, you know,
like cool. Uh
The thing is that sometimes in the
literature these extra steps or these
parts are as Jeff
as Jeff has said, not explicit enough.
So, it seems that everything falls from
you as what is to be a thing and then
you have a full theory of cognitive
neuroscience. And we are like, we don't
think so, right?
There are other
other other deep ideas at work there,
right? And but if
we go back to the to the to the that
quote,
um
it's also not about the kind of the the
the general possibility of the free
energy principle and active inference
and the Markov blanket
formalism, but more about how it is
presented in the literature sometimes,
right? So,
sometimes it is clear that you put
the blanket so in so to speak in the in
the faces space, not in the real space,
but in you know, you you just like some
states and then you put
the blanket there. And this is clear for
instance in one paper. I think it's
Michael Kirchhoff, Julian Kiverstein,
Karl Friston, and I don't know if I and
if I if I forget someone else, but they
actually model coupled
pendulums, right?
And
the blanket states there were something
I'm not completely sure, but were
something like velocity and
Yeah. relation or position acceleration.
These are not the the intuitive ones,
right?
This is not the the the surface of of of
of
of the pendulums, so to speak. But then
when you go to any figure in the in the
in in in the literature, you see the
blanket that is in the in the sensory
receptors or or or or in the membrane of
of of of the cell. When you expect
the blanket would would be from an
intuitive uh point of view. So, I would
put it that these two claims seems to be
not very well aligned, right? Either you
find the blanket in an in an abstract
state of space or or or in an
a space of states or or in an end
dimensional states of space and then the
blanket can be velocity acceleration
jerk, whatever you want, right? Or you
go to the more intuitive
uh way in which you know
the blanket of the cat is you know, I I
guess the hair or something. But
Like that. Or you find a way which which
I guess is the is the is the is the
ultimate aim, right? Uh you find a way
to align these two.
Maybe.
But I I I think the reason that this
happens though is because because the
principle is uniformly applicable to all
systems. And
you know, by
and all subsystems and all subsystems of
subsystems, they kind of like glossed
over that problem. It's like doesn't
matter what system you're interested in,
this theory applies.
Right? And I think that's one of the
reasons why like the issue that Vicente
brings up was basically glossed over.
Right? It's because it it was it wasn't
the you know, the the the the two
interesting questions if from my
perspective
that got glossed over are how do
blankets form in the first you know, how
how do the blankets that we would like
to call blankets cuz they're blankets
everywhere, but how are the interesting
how do interesting blankets form? Right?
What are the what are the mechanics that
that lead to that process? And then why
do we say this is an interesting blanket
than that is just a
a drop of or just a
a
fluid volume.
Blanking on the easy stuff now. Why why
yeah, why is that just a fluid? Why is
that an uninteresting blanket?
And this is where the whole like
parsimony thing comes in, right?
Interesting blankets have interesting
properties.
Right? And they simplify the overall
dynamics. But that but but if you if you
if you start out your paper by writing
that like oh well, I'm going to have
this other principle and it's going to
say this is a blanket and this is the
preferred blanket. Right? Then you sort
of it it it
it kind of tarnishes your ability to say
that your theory is uniformly applicable
to all systems and subsystems.
And I think that that is ultimately the
cause of this of of this particular
confusion.
You know, which is why but like you
know, you like when I saw this stuff, my
knee-jerk response is I why are they
saying a flame doesn't have a blanket?
Right? So, my I I I should mention my my
the title of my PhD thesis was like
what was it? Complex dynamics and solid
flame microstructure. We're actually
burning stuff.
And and the way that we model flames is
explicitly with a blanket. The blankets,
you know, is is is that there's the
flame it's burning this way down a fuse
like think Acme bomb, right? It's going
like this it's going down a fuse and
there's a blanket, right? The blanket is
basically just outside the reaction
zone. Right? In the same way that like
you know, fluid flowing or air going by
like an airplane wing forms a little
boundary which we call curiously enough
the boundary layer, right? Um and you
know, and that's a blanket, too. We are
constantly using blankets because they
simplify dynamics. And that was exactly
how I got to this you know, that's
exactly why to me that there was this
implicit parsimony principle that solved
that particular problem.
Excellent. Um but but I but I certainly
agree like you know, it was it was a
rhetorical choice, right? You want to
show that it it always applies. So, of
course I'm just going to randomly draw
blankets at at you know, as need be.
Because it always works.
I
I I like that idea in the in the in the
I mean in the in the spirit of
generality, they kind of gloss over
these tiny details that there are some
systems that might be tricky, right? But
I think there's kind of another
reason for that. I don't think it's a
it's a it's an opposite one. It's a it's
a complementary one. But in in it's a
reason that I think applies
um
mostly to psychology and neuroscience.
Um
like like Jeff, I don't I'm not a super
fan of the of what what they call the
high road to to the to the free energy
principle. Yeah, the the the random
dynamical system plus data. I like
better the one that comes from
predictive
processing and builds up, right? First
because I think it
it is
it it what happened historically, right?
With the with the with the
1990s paper on autoencoders to you know,
and
you can see that. And then
uh
because it
makes explicit how the free energy
principle within psychology and
neuroscience grows within a theory
within a novel of theory in which this
separation is already taken for granted.
Right? You see there are the internal
states of of of which are the brain that
are making the inference. There are some
blanket states, right? Which are
receptors. And there's some
environment. So, right? So, right this
kind of
blanket
formalism perfectly fit
the overall idea that there we have
internal states that have to infer the
external ones. So, it was not an issue
for kind of say the mainstream
psychology and neuroscience to think in
that way.
It was like taken for for for granted,
so to speak. But then this there's this
weird weird weird people called
ecological that have issues with that
thing. And and and of course that's from
that's the place from from where our
paper comes, right? We see issues in
that in some systems in that in that So
so
So, I'm going to propose like the happy
the happy middle ground here, right? So
So, the statement that all things behave
as if they are performing inference is
kind of hard to get around, right?
Because like it it literally follows
from I mean it's it it follows from
whether you take statistical physics or
information theory, it's sort of a
statement about like an
But what what it doesn't tell you is the
thing that is is
what it doesn't you know, so now you say
well, I don't think the brain is doing
inference or I don't think perception is
inference or something like that. It
turns out that's not incompatible with
with with what the free energy principle
states, either.
And the reason for this is because the
free energy principle says that all
things behave as if they are performing
inference. It says nothing about the
quality of that inference.
It could be really shitty inference. It
has to be good enough so that the thing
can maintain its boundary statistics,
the the statistics that define it as
like that type of a thing. But it could
in fact be really bad compared to what a
normative model of inference would be
would be performing. And I think that
this step this step has also been been
sort of or this this little bit has also
sort of been been missed.
Right? There there in in a lot of
applications because like especially
like what I do nowadays, which is like
you know, AI applications, you don't
want to find systems that do shitty
inference, right? You want to find
systems that do optimal inference.
Right? And so but but it but in
practice, right? That that becomes the
new question. It's sort of like well,
okay. So, they've shown that it it's
always doing inference.
And I'll just accept that, but I don't
care. I don't care because I'm
interested in the exact in in the kinds
of inference mistakes that it's making.
Right? It's kind of like saying like
when we're in the lab, right? So, we
I've worked with a lot of behavioral
scientists over the years. And when
they're in the lab, they always sit the
monkey down and okay, let's not do
monkeys.
Uh there's a mouse.
And the mouse is doing some task. And we
always want to ask questions like well,
how how well is the mouse doing this
sort of like this task? Now, we can
solve that problem because we designed
the task and we set the mouse to solve
it.
Right?
And so the we can sort of say oh well,
he's doing he's getting like 95% correct
or let's say he's getting doing 90%
correct. But the maximum he could given
the task difficulty, the best he could
possibly do is like you know, 9 9 98% or
96% correct like that. So, that's
comparing the animal's behavior to
optimal behavior.
And we do that a lot in the lab. But
when it comes to really complicated
things, we don't have we don't have that
we lose that ability.
Right? And this is where cognitive
psychology comes in, right? Cognitive
psychology is like okay,
there's no way in hell a human is going
to solve this really complicated social
dynamics problem optimally. In fact, we
don't even know how to write down the
solution to this really complicated
social dynamics problem properly. Now,
you might be able to say from this free
energy perspective that the person is
behaving as if they are solving it
probabilistically or as if they are
doing inference, but it's not optimal
inference. And so now, what what what
what becomes the interesting area of
investigation? The interesting area of
investigation is what are the mistakes
that someone is making. How do we
characterize those? Like, how do we just
characterize their behavior? Right? We
don't have to you know, if you're a
psychologist, you don't have to commit
to this as inference problem, right?
Because the the question that you want
to answer is not is it doing inference,
but it's what sort of you know, what
sort of mistakes are you making? What
sort of assumptions are you making? Not
which is a statement about the quality
of your inference algorithm,
which is much more interesting than
whether or not you're doing inference.
I think that's right. No, that's what
way more long-winded, so I apologize. I
meant that to be compact and concise. It
just didn't happen.
it's a it's a really No, it's a really
useful addition. Um
so,
backtracking 15 minutes just for the
audience. Um the paper that Vicente
mentioned is, I believe, uh Kirchhoff
and colleagues, 2018, the Markov
blankets of the Markov blankets of life.
I like just clarifying that in case
people want to backtrack and um I
believe that's the that's the blankets
of blankets one, right? Yeah, that's the
one with the pendulums.
So, I wanted to clarify that. To clarify
that.
Okay, this No, this is interesting. I
mean, again, we're getting on far too
well.
Um but no, we're doing well. We're doing
well. No No one's shouting at each other
yet.
Um okay, No, this is this is super. So,
so as you said, Jeff,
um we kind of need to do
approximate base sufficiently well that
we don't dissipate into the heat bath
or it looks like we're doing that. Um
and that's I I I feel like some of the
ways that issue got skirted is that we
would encode a higher order uh if we're
talking about humans, a higher order
prior preference that we believe that we
should be or we are minimizing
variational free energy.
So, there's
Yeah, no, I What Yeah, is that like kind
of uh Well, go ahead. Go ahead. I'm just
curious about your whole So, we we don't
have to believe anything about this,
right? In order to the the cell doesn't
have to believe in the free energy
principle. The point is is that it's a
mathematical inevitability, right? It's
it you know, uh
you know, so
you know, what So, I guess okay, so let
me let me go back. There are two ways to
think about the free energy principle,
and one of them has to do with like like
self-organization.
So, what is self-organization mean? It's
sort of like it sounds as if you're sort
of saying that like, oh, I have a notion
of self,
right? That that I act so as so that
that I act that you know, I take action
so that my notion of self is coherent.
I don't like any of that stuff. Um I
know that a lot of other people do, but
I like it cuz cuz the whole point is is
that you don't even need a notion of
self, right? We it you know, in order to
behave as if you have a notion of self.
Right? The way it's constructed, it's
sort of like, oh, okay, it has a
boundary. The boundary has these
statistics. What simply has to happen to
maintain those statistics? Those
statistics give us a notion of object
type, which you could call self,
and you could sort of say, well, okay,
for now, you know, then you could sort
of ask the question like, inside does it
also have this notion of self? I don't
think it's a meaningful question.
Right? It's you know, it's
Yeah, it's sort of like, well, we've you
we we've said like, this no you know,
this is the object type. This is its
definition, and we're really asking a
question, how do internal and external
states collaborate in order to maintain
the boundary? And if you take the if you
take the the max ND, you know, version
of the derivation, that becomes
explicit. What you're really asking is,
how do internal and external states
collaborate to maintain boundary
statistics?
That has nothing There's no notion of of
like self. Yes. I know, I I'm completely
on board with that. I do
some of the work that I like to focus on
is actually about self-modeling,
self-construction, um which completely
is opposed to the Cartesian ego picture.
And I think actually a lot of the
conceptual problems come from a
retention of the Cartesian ego that
people just feel very It's very
difficult to abandon that picture. No, I
I I was only adding this because
well, what you said is very much in line
with what Carl said when he came on,
which is that there is no real
existential imperative. It's just if you
can see object X at time here and object
X at the same supposed object at T plus
1, they've had to have done something
that looks like uh Bayesian inference.
So, it's a it's an existential
imperative
only in the sense that we can make the
we can we can kind of say that things
persist through time.
But there are these sort of added bells
and whistles, right? So, I you know, I'm
pretty sure there are papers. Now, maybe
these are earlier papers, which say
something like
there is a I've read it today. There's
an a priori belief. Now, whether this is
a propositional or subpersonal belief, I
think is somewhat trivial, that
I am And again, I'm saying this to make
sense. I am the type of thing that will
minimize variational free energy.
So,
given that, but given your uh point that
we can do quite shitty uh
variational Bayesian inference,
perceptual inference, for one, and okay,
Yeah, relatively Yeah, relative to
optimal, but yeah. Right. Our KL
divergences can be quite big. Um
what
Vicente, do you see a way of um
accounting for
the persistence of the organism
beyond just like this slow optimization
problem, um which, as I said, kind of
historically, at least, invoked this
higher order prior that I am type of
thing that will um do descent down free
energy gradients?
away. Well, I mean,
I guess this is a a question on on on
how the things persist in time or how
what we call things persist in time. So,
one thing is that I don't have any issue
with the with the mathematical
imperative part of it, right? Uh that's
part of I mean,
I can say something like, given these
and these
uh constraints, the
uh
dynamical system with with an attractor
will tend to that to that attractor, and
that's a mathematical
imperative, too, right? If you have an
attractor and with the constraint they
be, the system will tend to that. And
actually, you can redescribe that
tending towards the the the attractor in
terms of
Bayesian inference, in terms of
self self-information minimization,
whatever, or maximization, and free
energy, right? So, I don't have anything
about that.
Um
The thing is is that the way uh the
permanence of things or the
self-organization of things without the
belief of it has been uh studied in
time,
uh is
is the kind of thing that uh
touches on homeostasis, allostasis, or
even autopoiesis, right?
Um enactivists think that the thing what
the thing does is to is to self not not
only to self-organize, but to
self-produce
itself, right? The the
the in so to speak, the internal state
of the systems are engaged in
maintaining the boundary, right? That's
what they
what what they what they do there. And I
don't think they
they they picture that in terms of
having to believe that. They
basically
picture that in terms of
catalytic or even physiological ways to
maintain that, right?
Um
And and I guess that's that's that's
an account of homeostasis, too, of
allostasis when you include the
dynamical relationship with the with the
with the environment, right?
So, now, I guess the question is that to
what extent or the question we at least
we were interested in is to what extent
um
this physical imperative of the
minimization of
free energy or the or the performing as
if making Bayesian inference is able to
capture
autopoiesis,
for instance, right? And not only
autopoiesis, not only the
self-organization part, but the
self-production part.
Um
And we And that's another question we
have in the
Yeah, so so I have two I have two
answers, right? Uh the first is is that
when it comes to like maintenance,
maintenance is baked in, right? If you
if you say my definition of a thing is
that it has these boundary statistics,
and they're stationary statistics,
then you
it's baked in, right? You know, which is
totally fine. That's your definition of
that object type. It is stable,
right? And that you know, which is
great. The the hard question, and the
question that you know, that has been, I
think,
un that has gone largely unaddressed in
the FEP literature, is how do these
things form in the first place?
And this is right like you know, when
you say like, oh, it's a
you know, the focus has always been on
homeostasis, which has nothing to do
with starting from
a glob of goop,
right?
And getting something that is stable,
right? It doesn't have anything to do
Now, there's self-repair is in there,
right? And there is like finding a you
know, homeostasis of balance with your
environment, but there's nothing that is
how do I get from, you know, a chemical
soup to a cell?
That is
the FEP has has has historically,
you know, been completely agnostic on
that topic, right?
Um and that's one of the reasons why I
don't use words like, you know,
allostasis. I also forget what they mean
cuz that's a big word.
It's a really big word.
Um but
but but but but which it but but but
that said, there are in fact people
working on that particular problem.
That's why I like to cite like so I've
mentioned Jeremy England like twice now.
This is he gets he gets a third mention.
That's how cool I think he is. I also
just read his book which was which was a
lot of fun
and that's probably why it's on my mind.
So, the approach that he's taking is
well, okay, so that's the goal, right?
The goal is to say well, what you know,
what actually you know, why is it that
these that these complicated things form
apparently out of nothing?
And the math that he uses is is in fact
the mathematics of statistical physics
and the thing that he and the
you know, and the mathematical object
that seems to motivate this is
constructing free energy minimizing
flows.
Right?
Great. He even has a love I think it's
chapter seven in his book where he then
goes on to say, "And by the way, you
could think of the you know, these free
energy energy minimizing flows as doing
a kind of computation about their
environment." But he doesn't actually
say as if. I actually read through it
twice just to see if he used the phrase
as if and it turns out he doesn't which
is unfortunate.
But he makes a very similar argument,
right? Is is that is it you know, this
free energy minimization principle can
in fact also lead to the formation of
these things.
The math is a lot more complicated.
Right? And certainly static blankets
don't apply in this scenario. Like the
static a static Markov blanket doesn't
apply.
Right?
Um because the whole point is that over
time it's actually forming that blanket
is constantly changing and morphing into
a much more interesting set of
statistical that So, the the statistics
of the blanket are no longer stationary.
So, a stationary blanket doesn't work.
Um but the same free energy principle
applies. The same free energy principle
that Schrödinger called negative entropy
um
uh
or that was sometimes referred to as
negative entropy. It's it's and and the
reason for this is because it all falls
out ultimately from like statistical
physics. Okay. Fantastic. Well, yeah,
but but you're right. That has not
really been I mean, I just wanted to
reiterate. I did have a point when I
started the tirade. I just want to get
back to it.
You know, it is true that that hasn't
been addressed like how these blankets
actually form in the first place.
Is the free energy principle in its
current form has been largely agnostic
and that's why we say, "Well, take a
look what Jeremy England's doing. It's
basically free energy, too."
Okay, I'd like to get to that maybe as
also sort of closing
uh remarks cuz I don't think there's
going to be too much antagonism or or
discord there. I will raise one more
criticism that was um
mentioned in Ezequiel Di Paolo's
commentaries. So, this is his criticism
of the FEP and and and then we can move
on to the fluffy philosophy or
statistical mechanics, whatever it is.
Um
So, Ezequiel Di Paolo has two critiques
in a way of um
this uh of the FEP formulation.
The first is exactly what we've spoken
about which is that we have to make a
choice about where to carve up the
Markov blanket and we've covered that
until the cows come home although I'd be
always happy to return to that. But
his second point is and I will quote,
"Markov blankets are too strong to
account for the way the internal states
of an organism are often directly
affected by external states without any
statistical mediation or loss of
integrity as anyone who's ever been
tipsy after a few beers or felt dizzy
from heat exhaustion can verify."
So, now we're kind of we we've gone to a
completely different formulation which
is just no vicarious
blanket states.
Okay, the we're having direct effects.
Um
Jeff, I'm going to start with you
because
I your face
is telling me that you don't like that
so much. Um how does that sound to your
ears?
I I have no idea. I have no idea what is
meant by that.
Um it's sort of like I mean
And certainly the analogy that was
provided I do not understand.
I I suspect that either I mean, I'm
probably being obtuse or maybe I haven't
I'm not tipsy enough given the analogy I
thought.
Um but I don't understand how anything
can have a direct effect. I mean, you
know, I I can think of a another
scenario that one might appeal to to
make a similar argument which is like
and now let's talk about like protons
and electrons. They have electric
fields, right? And those fields have,
you know, an effect.
Right? But to my mind, that just means
you you know, your blanket is the field.
Right? Yeah.
Vicente, do you have any thoughts on
this?
Um
I was
I was imagining that Jeff
was not going to like that.
And and and and I do understand why,
right? I mean, it's kind of in the
in
in the very definition of a Markov
blanket is those sets of states that are
always there kind of, you know,
mediating between the the internal and
the
external.
I guess that what Ezequiel was trying to
point out there
is something like
it is possible for those blankets
blankets to be leaky sometimes. I think
this is an idea that that you find in
the in the weak Markov blankets
um
paper, too.
Uh
I know that that that that there's no
there's no absolute
fusion, so to speak, between the
internal and the and the and the
external states.
Uh and that's why they're weak, right?
Kind of there's not a full
encapsulation.
Uh this is just an an a speculation on
on on what's
Ezequiel pointed, right? That those
blanket maybe can be leaking in some way
sometimes.
Um Yeah, may maybe this is an issue that
I have difficulty understanding because
I've already moved on beyond in my
thinking like blankets don't have to be
static. Yeah.
Right? Cuz cuz the the best criticism of
of the original set of Markov blanket
stories was,
"Your basic your definition of a blanket
or at least the way you are using a
blanket
prohibits matter transfer
between object and environment. So, like
good luck describing something that
eats."
Think think you know, how right.
So, fortunately, you know, you know, the
the way around that originally was just
sort of say, "Oh, well, we could have
like made the blanket operate on fluxes
instead of particles." And I never
really liked that. You know, but but now
that we've gotten this issue where we've
basically said, "Oh, no, look. Dynamic
blankets, it all still works." Right?
All the math still works out just fine
even when there's matter transfer. It
works on flames. And so, to my if that
was the ultimate issue, then I would say
that issue has been resolved, but I
would understand why someone would have
drawn that conclusion from the
literature.
Um because the literature focused on
problems that were a lot more solvable.
Like the dynamic you know, identifying
dynamic Markov blankets is a really
mathematically challenging problem.
Yeah. Well, I Whereas specifying a
static one makes your life really easy.
And I you know, you know, you should
never be overly critical of people in my
view for, you know, simple mathematic
you know, mathematically mathematical
simplifications.
Right? You should always be generous and
say like, "Oh, I understand that that's
not part of the principle per se. That's
just the particular use of it." You
know, and my my favorite example of this
is is like general relativity.
You know, the the equation of general
relativity has like three terms. It's
like big G, little G, and T.
What they don't tell you is that hidden
behind those three terms there's a ton
of math which is why there's only like
one solution to that problem, right? Um
and the same sort of goes for the free
energy principle, right? If you actually
write down what the objective function
for active inference is, it's really
hard to compute. Yeah. And so, they
they've made a lot of assumptions and to
simplify the math and to make the
computation easier.
Right?
And so, you should always be I always
encourage people to be generous
when evaluating things in which there's
there are equations and then there's
simplifications.
You got to if you're evaluating the
theory, you got to evaluate the original
equations, right? And not criticize the
simplifications.
Very Christmasy.
Um maybe this
will help or uh or not or maybe it might
muddy the waters.
Another
quote now from the Markov blanket trick.
Um
"Without the Markov blanket formalism,
the dual information geometry would be
reduced to its intrinsic component which
is the only one needed for standard
thermodynamics." And I've written next
to that on my note, "Why don't we just
use this?"
Jeff, why don't we just use this?
Because we want I I really do think
because like at the heart of a lot of
this is like phenotyping.
Mhm. It's sort of like the goal is
actually to segment the universe into
little understand into smaller
understandable pieces.
Right? And since if that's the goal,
then it it that's that's sort of, you
know, I sort of I feel like I addressed
this before when I said like, you know,
if we could model the whole universe,
like no problem. Like why would we
bother to chop it up in the little
pieces and sort of say, "Oh, no, this is
a car. I'm going to summarize car
dynamics. I'm going to worry about the
little bits and part bit bits and pieces
inside." Cuz I could, you know, why
would you do that if you could just
simulate the whole thing and it was no
problem. Right? So, there's sort of this
there's sort of an empirical question
here. Like that's why the reason we
divide things up, the reason we draw
blankets around things is to make our
lives is to make our ability to
understand the universe more tractable,
right? It's to make it's to make it
easier to get.
Right? Reason why, you know, it's like
you could always simulate everything if
you could. You really can't. But like if
you could, you would.
But you can't, right? You you're looking
for cognitive shortcuts if you're a
cognitive scientist. You're looking if
you're a a scientist, you're looking for
simplifications of complex systems.
You're looking for macroscopic
variables.
It's a
It's so it's sort of like there's an
empirical reason why you would do that.
Vicente, have you got anything to add
and maybe I should have asked exactly
what this claim
entails, what what the reduction to an
intrinsic component actually looks like.
I'll tell you I that was
I wouldn't say a quote, but that was
very bad team almost from from from the
from the dual
geometry
papers, right? So, it was more than
saying
more than focusing in the reduction you
would do, I think what what the what
what the the the free energy principle
proponents are saying they're like,
"Look, this is just
thermodynamics extended a little bit
because we have these these these
blanket that they allow us to do this
this other thing, right?" So, that's
what what I think. And actually,
I I'm going to one more time agree with
Jeff
in
And
I think that again that was that was
kind of the spirit of the Markov blanket
trick to try to go ourselves through the
through other things that you need for
for the for the whole building to be
built,
so to speak. And of course, you need to
you need to to choose the the the thing
you are interested in. You need to make
assumptions on, "Okay, these are the
variables I'm going to be working with."
And with all that, I mean,
ecological psychologists are pretty much
the first people that during the '80s
who started using dynamical systems
theory to to model
behavior. Actually, there's there's a
there's a 1987 book
by
Peter Kugler and Michael
Turvey called
Information Natural Law and Rhythmical
Behavior. If you go there and read
how they gather from statistical physics
and all that stuff, you see many similar
points than than than than you see now
in the in in the in the free energy
principle realm, right? But the point
being
when I say, "Okay, we we model or we,
you know, that within
within this kind of dynamic cognitive
science, there's a very famous model,
the HKV model of coupled oscillators in
in which the the the the main variable
is relative phase.
Why is it relative phase? Well, it's a
it's a variable very easy to track and
when you track it and you and you model
it,
you have a
very cool two attractors for these
parameters and you change and and you
see how the how the two attractors go to
one. So, you you can you can express the
qualitative
changes of of the of the coupling of the
two oscillator in a very simple way with
just one variable. And you know,
but why you pick that one? Well,
because, you know, it's it it it's easy
and and and it model it
well, right? So,
so, I mean, I
obviously agree with Jeff
on that. The point was, yes, in the
literature,
these simplifications sometimes are not
clear.
And Yeah. It's good to to to
I think they
and and I also understand, yes, they are
not clear because the aim was
generality, right? So, we want this to
apply to everything. So, when when when
the coupled
oscillators guy come, but no, but talk
about my thing. Oh, okay. To to to talk
That's right. Yeah. We need to put all
these other things as to make it work,
right? So, that kind of thing. Yeah, and
that's one of the reasons why I really
got to get this paper out. So,
basically, it's it's, you know, if you
another way to think about what, you
know, the Markov blanket story is is
that it's it's an integral component not
just of systems identification theory,
but also like macroscopic physics
discovery.
Right? So, why did you pick the phase
difference? It was a convenient
variable. It encapsulated all of the
dynamics.
Right? What if your problem was, "I just
have a complex system and I don't know
what and I need to discover what the
phase variables should be."
Right? And the Markov blanket story is
one way to do that, right? It's sort of
like I want to segment my complex system
into different subsystems and if you
have a
Markov blanket discovery algorithm,
right? Then it sort of does that for
you. It does macroscopic physics
discovery.
That that
It identifies that that was the simplest
variable to use.
That makes me wonder
out of
the blue, so I don't have an answer to
the
this is a pure question that might not
have an answer. When
when people who work with dynamical
systems or at this part of them to model
motor control, right? They they they
gather a lot of ideas from Bernstein and
from Haken and the idea of
synergy, right? Like like the brain is
able to to control the arm as a synergy
because it's already coordinated
as a as a as a whole unit there. Could
you put
So, could you put a Markov a Markov
blanket
on a synergy, so to speak?
I don't know. So, I think that that So,
so to some extent and
So, and this is a I'm going to just sort
of say this is a gross generalization of
what the discover of what the blanket
discovery algorithm does.
But in a in a very real way, right? It's
doing dimensionality reduction, right?
Which is basically identity synergy
identification. Right? So, why is it
that like, you know, I can model I can
just sort of look look at all this
complicated stuff I can do. Well, it
turns out, right? There's really only
like a very small number of variables I
have to track because you you know,
they're all correlated, right? There are
restrictions or they're constrained,
right? My wrist is the same distance
from my elbow like and so on.
And so, that's another way of character
Well, that means they're correlated,
right? And synergy and correlations are
very are sort of, you know, are related.
And so, to some extent what the
algorithm actually does or when you're
doing Markov blanket discovery, what
you're basically saying is what's
correlated?
What aspects of the dynamical system are
sufficiently strongly related that I can
reduce them to a single variable? Right?
So, for example, for a rigid body,
right?
I can describe this whole thing by two
points, right? I, you know, because you
know, I don't have to model every single
molecule in my arm, right? I can reduce
it to a single variable.
And that's the another way of thinking
about like again, macroscopic physics
discovery.
Um
Right.
But I also think that's one of the
reasons why like the FEP is as it's
formulated is strongly tied to just
empiricism, right? It's it's it has a
lot to do with just how we do science,
right? We're we're doing like
dimensionality reduction and looking for
principles that uniformly apply.
Um and and I think that the focus of the
literature has been on the uniformly
applied thing.
And now we need to bring it into the
real world of empirical inference where
it's the dimensionality reduction thing.
But they are in fact completely
compatible.
Amazing. Uh just again to loop round to
what I had said so that people know
where to go. The the quote that I
chose is footnote 12 of the Markov
blanket trick. I told you I read the
paper.
Um and I think it pertains to this two
complementary ways of describing the
density dynamics of internal states, one
being this intrinsic
change over time towards the attractor
state and then the other one is this
extrinsic um tracking of external
states.
And I'm not a mathematician, but it
appears to me that the maths
seems equivalent. Um
and we can actually make a kind of
formal equivalence between those things,
which is quite
useful, actually. It's It's almost as if
they're equivalent.
I'm not a mathematician. Give me a
break.
No, no, no, no, no. Sorry, that was that
was not a criticism. That was a terrible
joke. Oh, okay. Fine.
Fine. Oh, right. Yes. Yes, very good.
Very good. It looks like they're the
same.
Um
Yeah, excellent. So,
I will finish with what I promised we'd
finish with, which is a kind of big
potentially philosophical question that
expands beyond the scope of the free
energy principle as it is right now.
Um and this is an issue that actually is
really matters to me. When I first
discovered active inference, I remember
tweeting two things. One of which was
the presence of Markov blankets upon
Markov blankets is the best argument
from creation that's ever been.
And the second one was um
I think that the apparent distinctions
of internal and external states mediated
for a Markov blanket might itself be an
illusion.
And there may just be some sort of
singular reality. I'm paraphrasing my
silly tweets. But it was more just
philosophical
theory or thinking.
And we mentioned panpsychism earlier.
Um
and again, I don't want to get too into
the weeds on this. But Jeff, maybe we
could start with you.
Where do you think this all comes from
these um these distinctions that we can
carve for instrumental reasons, which
seem to you know, which do work
mathematically? And
what are your hunches about what might
lie underneath them?
Mhm.
I love questions like this and I have
the perfect answer. So, what lies
underneath? Nothing.
Oh, that That was my serious face.
That doesn't help.
No, no, so so I remember one time I got
asked a question
like you know, so we're talking about
like
you know, P's and Q's cuz that's what
you're doing when you're doing
probabilistic reasoning and somebody
raised their hand and said, "Is there a
true P?"
The answer is no. No, no, there's not.
And it's not because there isn't a true
P, right? It's just I don't understand
the question, right? It's sort of a it's
sort of a jerky thing to say. I I often
describe when I when when I get So, as
you might imagine given what I do for a
living, I get asked questions like that
all the time. I usually refuse to
answer.
And the reason I refuse to answer is
because I got up to work today. I put on
my coat and tie and I put on my work
pants, right? My work pants are my harsh
instrumentalist pants.
And if you want me to answer like
philosophical or religious questions,
it's like, "Well, I have to put on a
different pair of pants."
Right? Uh you know, when you know,
when functioning in this in this
environment like
you know, it's it it it you know, I I
take a very very instrumentalist view,
right? And I think the you know, so you
asked like, "Oh, do we carve you know,
is there some is it all just one thing?
Right? Are these artificial carvings
artificial?" The artificial carvings are
artificial.
Like we carve up the world because it's
convenient, right? Because it simplifies
the problems we have to solve. It has
empirical it has predictive power and
empirical utility. I like to say that
science is not about truth, it is about
prediction and data compression
and nothing else.
Right? So, when functioning as a
scientist, that's what I focus on.
Which is my way of saying like that's
that's my answer. Harsh instrumentalism.
Harsh instrumentalism means you don't
have to worry about like what's true.
I can't wait for all the philosophers to
be shouting at you virtually. Um
Vicente.
What are your thoughts on this?
I was expecting this answer from Jeff
because my preparation to this podcast
was not to reread my own paper, but to
to watch another podcast on the on the
on the machine learning street talk, I
think.
And yeah. And that he was saying
electron is just the name for an
equation, you know, like the
that's
right. So, so I was
expecting harsh instrumentalism.
I can I'm kind of an I'm I'm
I'm kind of an instrumentalist, too.
In some ways.
Uh but at the same time, I'm a realist.
So, how can that be? How can that be the
case, right?
Uh I I can get it's it it comes from
real um
comes all to to form of pragmatism in
the end in which you can be realist
about the kind of things you do.
Uh and if they are successful, well, you
you you are dealing with the with the
with the real world.
And
um you do so by using instruments.
And I'm I'm
in favor of a plurality of instruments.
Uh and Markov blankets are one of them.
But I I don't personally use in my own
research, right? But you can use it.
Um but I wouldn't try to find
a final foundation like, "Oh, there's
only one thing."
Um
or or you know, or everything is such or
everything is such other thing, right?
It's more like
uh we act around um
and
reality somehow the way all where all
our actions
converge.
Um and not actually. Sometimes do,
sometimes don't. And and we we carve
reality in that way and
all we have is our our concepts that are
instruments and and our you know,
not foundational in any way. Tools.
Markov blankets, other tools. And we go
like that. But I mean, I don't think
there's there's a there there there's
some form of
you know, uh
matter of fact or fact of of of of the
matter. So,
so to be So, there's something that that
there's something that we
some reality that we build up together
through action and it's there. It's just
it can change. So, it's not the final
thing. It's it's it's it's it's not the
an all the philosopher, you know, an
ancient philosopher
would say something like the the arche,
right? The the this this this final
original thing. There's no But there's a
thing we do that there's there's a
there's there's a matter of fact and um
the variety of tools and their
superposition and their big clues or big
or big clues. I don't know that that
that word in English. But even the even
the things that they don't match well
tell us thing about what
what kind of thing we can do and we can
not.
Oh, where are my Buddhist friends? Where
are my Where are my Well, so that's
that's the funny thing. You asked the
wrong question. If you wanted me to put
my put on my Quaker Buddhist pants, I
can do that, too. Oh, we might I just I
just generally refuse to. Maybe on
Christmas day, I'll ask. Yeah.
It's one of those
It's like I reme- I remember one of my
my
one of my
one of the faculty in my department when
I was getting my PhD
once said that um
uh
philosophy is a lot like like algebra or
or or going to the bathroom. It's just
not something you should do in public.
So, I I don't agree with that. I think
you know,
it it indicates like why it is that I
hesitate to answer these questions cuz I
don't really have good answers. I have
my answers. And defaulting to
instrumentalism is like just the easy
way out, right?
Sure.
Well, yeah, they're they're they're
purposefully quite provocative and
probing. Uh but people seem to like
answering them.
Chaps, that was uh
that was tremendously fun.
Um
maybe we could have just a couple
minutes for closing remarks um given
we've reached such a beautiful point of
conciliation. Vicente.
Maybe in addition to sort of closing
remarks, you could also let people know
what you're working on and where they
could reach out to you if they wanted to
know more about your topics of interest.
Mhm. Okay. So, I'm going to start
by by talking one one last time about
the Markov blanket trick.
The paper kind of
you want its own. It's way long. I think
it's it's 24,000 words. So, it's it's
way it's way longer than
I was expecting.
Uh
uh because actually most most of it is
just uh
me asking a question No, not me. We all
of us, right? But asking the questions
we have, right? Oh, but if if the
formalism worked, why this and why that
and why candle flames and why you know,
that kind of thing.
But
I really don't have a strong
position on those things. I I just would
like to know, "Okay, how would you apply
these to a model with relative phase?"
And that that seems to include the whole
system.
I only have a strong opinion with one
thing.
Um which is
the fact that for
perception, you need or not need prior
knowledge.
Right? That's that's that's
actually the real
my my real estate there. Like I think
um every time you endorse the system
with some prior knowledge in order to
make sense to go as as we thought from
the
from the um unpublished in published
input to the real world, so to speak.
Uh you have no way to justify that that
that
knowledge or to explain what's why it is
there, right? The typical way you know,
what is say, "Oh, it's
evolution." Right?
But it's kind of
unsatisfactory for many things. I don't
want to go to this thing, right? But
this is actually my only
kind of my my deal
breaker. I think
theories of
perception should then appeal to prior
knowledge to explain.
And I think one theory that that does
that is ecological
psychology. By virtue of the lawful
relationship between the patterns of
light and the environment you have in
those patterns of light information
enough
as to know exactly what the exactly to
to to to a good
degree
what the what the real environment is
with without the need of pulling other
kind of knowledge into the equation. And
I work on that, right? So, so so so part
of
my work is is is
trying to sense
of cognitive neuroscience that starts
with ecological
psychology. For instance,
if the brain is not in the business of
inferring the real causes of
impoverished stimulation or of enriching
impoverished stimulation with all their
knowledge as to build a model of the
environment, what the hell is the is is
is the brain doing, right?
So,
within the ecological approach, the word
uses resonance.
The brain resonates to this richer
information. And
part of my theoretical work is to try to
operationalize the resonance metaphors,
so to speak. So, how can we have a a
concept that we can actually test?
And part of my empirical work, I'm kind
of maybe 70% of philosopher, 30% of
cognitive scientist, cognitive
neuroscientist, is to try to test that.
So, this year I've been in in in in the
B Mobile Lab, which is at the Technical
University of of
Berlin, and they and they
specialize in mobile EEG.
And so, I've been gathering some
multimodal data that that that has, you
know, eye tracking, motion capture, and
EEG
to try to find what kind of patterns of
information our brain can be resonating
to. So, how the brain dynamics can be
constrained by these specific structures
and not just by by by kind of say simple
input and that kind of thing. So, I'm
trying to Yeah.
Last
sentence, I'm trying to do something
like
ecological neuroscience
both in the theoretical realm and the
and and the experimental
realm.
Very cool. Very cool.
Jeff,
go ahead.
Uh
So,
I'm taking the exact opposite approach.
I'm trying to see how far we can push
this whole prior thing.
I I like to joke that the the difference
between a Bayesian and a non-Bayesian is
honesty, right? Is you have priors.
Right? I don't know where they come
from. I don't know that they're
normative, but they're there. You you're
kind of stuck with them. All knowledge
is like Laplace. All knowledge is based
on
um is all knowledge is probabilistic,
right? It's always based on assumptions.
There are two sets of assumptions that
are critical to worry about. One is I'm
going to get to what I'm doing in a
second.
One is the data, right? Any conclusions
you draw is conditioned on your
observations.
But there's another important thing that
we often forget about, right? Is that
all of the conclusions you draw are also
conditioned on your models for the
universe. And I say models, this is just
my view. I can see Vicente's going, "Oh
my god." No, um when I say models, I
actually think the most critical thing
that we often neglect when we talk about
the Bayesian brain is that there's not
one model.
There's a lot of them.
And they and and they and and you don't
just use one at a time.
Right? You use lots of them. In fact,
you want you could even think, and this
is very coarse. I'm going to I literally
I'm going to get to what I'm doing in a
second. It's very coarse, but you could
think of a Bayesian brain as having
brain regions, right? And don't over
parse this cuz I know people will,
right? And each region is a model.
Right? Each region describes is a
statistical model of something. And when
you get a new task, what do you do,
right? Well, you have to figure out
which collection of models and how
they're connected,
right? Are the is you know, are the ones
that like solve your problem.
Or model or model the data or describe
the data or compactly summarize this
like the data compression. It compactly
summarize the information that you
receive or give you the predictions
about the things you care about or
however you want to phrase it.
And so, what we're trying to do right
now is we're exploring Sorry, we're
exploring the extent to which we can get
this to work at you know, at scale.
So, we want to construct a brain that's
not like some fast feedforward neural
network, right? But one that is more
brain-like,
right? By summarizing what by saying
that No, no, no, a brain has lots of
there's lots and lots and lots of
models. And the way that a brain
actually attacks problems is by
reasoning by analogy. This model
explains this part of what's going on.
This model explains this part of what's
going on. And the trick is how do you
figure out how to connect them? And so,
this is a massive model comparison
Bayesian graph neural networky
type problem, which is like
computationally intensive. Like I guess
that's a
I'd I'd I'd put that in quotes. Like but
it would like it would be like several
sets. That's that's how much scare it
is.
That's what we're working, right? We're
working on pushing, you know, seeing how
far we can really push this Bayesian
brain hypothesis, but not just for
saying there's a prior by saying there's
lots of them and they interact in
interesting ways. And at that point, is
it still a prior, Vicente? Or has it
become something else?
Right?
I mean,
Uh uh
This is kind of the of the agreement I I
I I reached with
Matz Woll, for example, with other
people there, right? Yeah, I mean, and I
think it is good. I I don't like the the
the idea of
of of prior knowledge or one prior or
many of them. I think there are other
ways. We like to talk about ecological
constraints that are not inside here,
out there. Well, but blah blah blah blah
blah. But
what I try to try try to do is to is no
priors. Let's see how far I can go.
And it's
that you guys do, okay, this this set of
of of priors, let's see how far. And
that's it. That's I think that's good
for science, actually.
Yeah.
No, that's the whole point, right? Cuz
eventually what we want to do is
Bayesian model comparison
between your approach and mine cuz you
know, Bayesian is the only way to do it,
obviously.
I think you guys are going to be in the
middle.
the absolute pleasure. Absolute pleasure
chatting with Thank you for
Well, it's No, it's been an absolute
pleasure to witness it. Um
thank you guys for coming on the
podcast. And
uh I'm sure there are some people out
there, devilish people, who expected
pots and pans to be thrown across
webcams. But um
it I I'm you know, this is what science
is about at the end of the day. Um
finding convergent paths and trying to
get closer to some approximation of
truth. So, I hopefully we've
contributed. Sorry, no. And you both
leaned back simultaneously. You want to
say that one? Um okay. Some something
that helps us predict and data compare.
There you go, Jeff. Um
but thank you guys again from me and the
institute. And
uh
yeah, everyone listening, definitely
check out Jeff and Vicente's work. So,
thank you again.
Thank you.